A Guide to the Ellen Frank Armentrout Papers, 1961-1964: SC 0064
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Ellen Frank Armentrout Papers,
1961-1964
Special Collections, James Madison University
Armentrout, Ellen Frank, 1943-
SC 0064
.12 Cubic Feet; 3 letter folders
The Ellen Frank Armentrout Papers, 1961-1964, are comprised of facsimiles of one essay, seven letters, and 15 photographs from Armentrout's time as a student at Madison College.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
During the spring of 2004, Ellen Frank Armentrout loaned her Madison College scrapbook to Dr. Phil Bigler, formerly of the James Madison Center, who passed it along to Pam Brock, former editor of Montpelier magazine, who forwarded it to Chris Bolgiano, former Special Collections Librarian. Bolgiano requested permission to copy the papers and photographs for inclusion in Special Collections. Armentrout granted permission to have the materials copied and the scrapbook was returned on May 5, 2004.
Other Formats Available
Low-resolution digital surrogates of the photographs are available for research (see below). Armentrout's September 1962 photograph of her dorm room in Sheldon Hall is also available at JMU Historic Photos Online.
Bio/Historical Note
Ellen Frank Armentrout (b. 1943), daughter of John W. and Edith Baldwin Frank of Arlington, Virginia, matriculated into Madison College in the fall of 1961. Her freshman roommate was Maryanne Matthews. Armentrout served as Recreation Chairman of the Wesley Foundation and graduated in 1965 with a Bachelor of Science degree. She married Donald Lee "Jack" Armentrout of Keezletown, Virginia in 1964. He attended Madison College as a day student and served as the sports editor of The Breeze. Many of Armentrout's letters home to her parents describe her courtship with Jack.
Scope and Content
The Ellen Frank Armentrout Papers, 1961-1963, are comprised of facsimiles of one essay on adjusting to college life, seven letters to her parents, and 15 photographs from Armentrout's time as a student at Madison College including May Day celebrations and dorm rooms. The materials originated from Armentrout's scrapbook which she loaned to Special Collections for selective digitization.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series 1: Papers, 1961-1963
Series 2: Photographs, 1962-1964
Both series are arranged chronologically.
Location of Originals
Original papers and photographs are retained by the donor.
Bibliography
The Breeze, May 11, 1962. Harrisonburg (Va.): Madison College.
The Breeze, September 10, 1964. Harrisonburg (Va.): Madison College.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- History; Madison College -- Alumni and alumnae; Madison College -- Students; Madison College -- Students -- Social life and customs; James Madison University -- Students -- History; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Facsimiles (reproductions); Black-and-white photographs; Digital images; Essays
- Series 1: Papers, 1961-1963
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Papers, 1961-1963, includes an essay commenting on adjusting to college life. Armentrout writes: "You say you love college and you're getting D's in all your classes? You say you cut three classes today so you could play bridge?....Don't despair, keep your chin up: it's all an adjustment to college. I'm having the same troubles."
  This series also includes seven letters written by Armentrout to her parents between March 1962 and May 1963. She provides detailed accounts of student life, extracurricular and social activities, dating, classes and coursework, and weather. Of particular interest is her letter of March 9, 1962 in which she describes a historic snow storm. Thirty-six inches of snow fell in Harrisonburg and, as a result, the students were allowed to wear slacks to class. A photo of the storm is included in this collection. In many of her letters, Armentrout describes the dating scene at Madison and comments on her social life. Of her future-husband Jack she writes: "Jack and I have a date tonight. I must confess I was wrong on two accounts about him. First – his car does have its original paint and Second – he plans to teach science and minor in biology. Everything else I said still holds true and even more so. He is a good guy."
  - Essay, 1961 (Box:folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box:folder 1:2)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1962-1964
  Series 2: Photographs, 1962-1964, is comprised of 15 facsimiles (and low-resolution digital surrogates) of color and black-and-white photographs taken while Armentrout was a student at Madison College. One image of the historic March 1962 snowstorm that blanketed Harrisonburg with 36 inches of snow is included. Also included are two images of dorm room interiors including a color image of Cleveland Hall, Room 106 and a black-and-white image of Sheldon Hall, Room 14; ten images of May Day celebrations (1962-1964); one image of the Smothers Brothers' November 1962 performance in the Keezell gym; and an undated image of downtown Harrisonburg.
  - Photographs, 1962-1964 (Box:folder 1:3)
    - Snowstorm, 1962
    - May Day (image 1), 1962
    - May Day (image 2), 1962
    - May Day (image 3), 1962
    - May Day (image 4), 1962
    - May Day (image 5), 1962
    - Sheldon Hall, Room 14, 1962
    - Cleveland Hall, Room 106, 1962
    - Smothers Brothers, 1962
    - May Day (image 1), 1963
    - May Day (image 2), 1963
    - May Day (image 1), 1964
    - May Day (image 2), 1964
    - May Day (image 3), 1964
    - Court Square, undated